Finding Aid for the Collection of Cuban Railroad Documents LSC.2334
UCLA Library Special Collections
Collection of Cuban railroad documents
1841-1867
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2334
1.2 linear feet (3 boxes)
Cuban railway history began in 1834 with the Compañía de Caminos de Hierro de La Habana, which primarily transported sugar from Güines to Havana. The Collection of Cuban railroad documents range from 1841-1867 and contains manuscript documents from the Compañía de Caminos de Hierro de la Habana and other Cuban railway companies, covering over twenty years of history of the Cuban railway system. Documents include concessions for the creation of new lines, agreements, records of meetings, shareholder lists, and financial reports. Most documents contain letterhead seals and engravings of the railway companies and government offices, with signatures of notable Cuban functionaries and politicians. Source: "Cuban Railroadiana: A manuscript archive, 1841-1867." Libros Latinos.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Libros Latinos, 2016.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9993510613606533
Biographical / Historical
Cuban railway history began in 1834 with the Compañía de Caminos de Hierro de La Habana, which primarily transported sugar from Güines to Havana.
Source: "Cuban Railroadiana: A manuscript archive, 1841-1867." Libros Latinos.
Content Description
The Collection of Cuban railroad documents range from 1841-1867 and contain manuscript documents from the Compañía de Caminos de Hierro de La Habana and other Cuban railway companies, covering over twenty years of history of the Cuban railway system. Documents include concessions for the creation of new lines, agreements, records of meetings, shareholder lists and financial reports. Most documents contain letterhead seals and engravings of the railway companies and government offices, with signatures of notable Cuban functionaries and politicians.
Source: "Cuban Railroadiana: A manuscript archive, 1841-1867." Libros Latinos.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged according to its existing order.
Railroads -- Cuba; Compañía de Caminos de Hierro de La Habana
- Concession for construction of Jucaro Railroad, 1841
- Communication from Conde de Peñalver regarding Jucaro Railroad, 1842
- New railway line from Matanzas to Coliseo, 1845
- Concession for construction of Coliseo Railroad, 1846
- Report from Regla/Matanzas Railway Company, 1846
- Concession for construction of Cárdenas Railway, 1849
- Concession for construction of Sabanilla Railway, 1849
- Report from Bay of Havana Railway Company, 1849
- Report from Caminos de Hierro de La Habana Company, 1850
- Report from the president of the Matanzas/Sabanilla Railway, 1851
- Report from the Railways and Telegraph Commission, 1852
- Report from the president of the Cárdenas Railway Company, 1853
- Report from the Government Engineers on Railways in Havana, 1853
- Report from the Government Engineers on Railways in Havana, 1853
- Contracts for work on Havana Railway, 1854
- Report from the Governor on regulations for railway companies, 1854
- Report from management and a list of shareholders of Cárdenas Railway, 1856
- Report from Central Railway Company on the island of Cuba, 1856
  Scope and Contents
  The report is signed by Captain General Concha.
- Record of the foundation of Bay of Havana/Matanzas Railway, 1857
- Record of the foundation of Railway Company of Santiago de Cuba, 1857
- Report on construction of Cárdenas/Jucaro Railway, 1857
- Report from Jucaro Railway Company, 1857
- Record of foundation of Regla/Matanzas Railway, 1857
- Report from Havana Railway Company, 1857
- Record of foundation of Oeste Railway Company, 1858
- Record of foundation of Guanabacoa Railway Company, 1858
- Report on Marianao Railway Company, 1858
- List of shareholders of Oeste Railway Company, 1858
- Report from Camino de Hierro de Cárdenas Railway Company, 1858
- Report from Cárdenas/Jucaro Railway, 1858
- Report from Public Works on Cárdenas/Jucaro Railway, 1858
- Report from Jucaro Railway Company, 1858
- Merger of Regla/Matanzas and 2nd Steam Railway of Havana Companies, 1859
- Report on Oeste Railway Company by Anson Taylor and John Bainsdor, 1860
  The report is signed by Anson Taylor and John Bainsdor.
- Reports on derailments and other accidents, 1860
- Report from Sabanilla/Maroto Railway Company, 1861
- Record of a general meeting at Marianao Railway Company, 1861
- Record of a board of directors meeting at Oeste Railway Company, 1861
- Record of foundation of Marianao Railway Company, 1861
- Record of a general meeting and a list of shareholders, 1861
- Record of a general meeting and a list of shareholders from Matanzas Railway Company, 1861
- Oeste Railway Company, 1861
- Report on the railways by Government Insurance Board, 1861
- Report on Sabanilla/Maroto Railway Company, 1861
- Report from Government Insurance Board on railway companies, 1861
- Report on Marianao Railway Company, 1861
- Report from Caminos de Hierro Railway Company, 1861
- Report from Caminos de Hierro Railway Company, 1861
- Report from Havana/Guanabacoa Railway Company, 1861
- Report from Havana Railway Warehousing, 1862
- Record from a general meeting at Oeste Railway Company, 1862
- Record from board meeting at Oeste Railway Company, 1862
- Economic report from Santiago de Cuba Railway, 1862
- List of shareholders of Matanzas Railway Company, 1862
- Reports from Oeste Railway Company written by its President D. Joaquin Pedroso, 1862
- Report from the Bahia de la Habana Railway Company, 1862
- Report from the Bahia de la Habana Railway Company, 1862
- Reports from Oeste Railway Company written by its President D. Joaquin Pedroso, 1862
- Report from Oeste Railway Company, 1863
- Record from a shareholders meeting at Marianao Railway Company, 1863
- Set of laws and regulations for railway guards, undated
- Record of a shareholders meeting including shareholders list from Jucaro Railway Company, undated
- List of shareholders of Marianao Railway Company, 1863
- Report from the Empresa Unida Railway Company, 1863
- Circular letter from the government regarding railways on the island, 1863
- Reports from Matanzas Railway Company, 1864
- Report from the Bahia de la Habana/Matanzas Railway Company, 1864
- Record from a shareholders meeting at Marianao Railway Company, 1864
- Marianao Railway Company loan application, 1864
- Report from Bahia de la Habana Railway Company, 1864
- Shareholders meetings at Marianao Railway Company, 1865
- Reports from Oeste Railway Company written by its President D. Joaquin Pedroso, 1865
- Record of a general meeting at Bahia de la Habana Railway Company, 1865
- Report on railways in Santiago de Cuba, 1865
- Report on railways in Santiago de Cuba, 1865
- Report on railways in Santiago de Cuba, 1865
- Report from Captain General on Marianao Railway Company, 1865
- Report from Oeste Railway Company on the Havana/Pinar del Rio line, 1865
- Report from Marianao Railway Company signed by its President Salvador Sama, 1865
- Report on railways in Santiago de Cuba, 1866
- Economic report from Matanzas Railway Company, 1866
- Record of general meeting at Railway Company, 1866
- Report from the Presidency of Railways in Santiago de Cuba, 1866
- Report from Habana Railway Company, 1867
- Report from financial meeting at Oeste Railway Company, 1867
- Record from a general membership meeting at railway company, 1867